[音乐]
[MUSIC]
&gt；&gt；Douglas：第四集，Ajax的变形记。
&gt;&gt; Douglas: Episode Four, The Metamorphosis of Ajax.
整个世界是一个页面，所有的男人和女人只是指针和点击器。
All the world's a page and all the men and women merely pointers and clickers.
所以，我们将从约翰·哈灵顿爵士开始。
So, we're gonna start this hour with Sir John Harrington.
诗人，朝臣，英国女王伊丽莎白一世的风流教子，
The poet, courtier, the saucy godson of Queen Elizabeth I of England,
作为一名发明家，今天被铭记于心，他发明了一种
is best remembered today as being an inventor, and he invented one of
使我们这个规模的文明成为可能的基本发明。
the fundamental inventions which makes civilization at our scale possible.
没有他的突破，我们就不能生活在城市里，
Without his breakthrough, we could not live in cities,
我们不可能生活在技术成就所必需的密度中。
we could not be living in the density necessary for technological achievement.
伟大的进步，所以这是他的发明的书中的一张图片。
Great move forward, so this is a picture from his book of his invention.
有人能认出它吗？
Can anybody identify it?
&gt；&gt；扬声器2：厕所。
&gt;&gt; Speaker 2: A toilet.
&gt；&gt；道格拉斯：这是一个抽水马桶，
&gt;&gt; Douglas: It is a flush toilet,
事实上，没有它们，文明就不能工作。
indeed, just civilization couldn't work without them.
罗马人有冲水技术，但当帝国崩溃时，它就消失了，
The Romans had flush technology, but it was lost when the Empire collapsed,
但哈林顿重新发现了它
but Harrington rediscovered it and
他为女王建造了一个这样的设备，并将其安装在她的住宅中。
he built one of these devices for the Queen and installed it in her residence.
而且，就像通常发生在真正重要的发明中一样，
And, as usually happens with the really important inventions,
她拒绝使用它。
she refused to use it.
她抱怨它太吵了。
She complained that it made too much noise.
她不想让城堡里的每个人都知道她什么时候去找她
She didn't want everybody in the castle knowing when she was going about her
皇家商业，所以它从来没有被使用过。
Royal Business, so it never got used.
但是，他出版了一本关于它的书，并且
But, he published a book about it, and
最终，其他发明家看到了它，并对其进行了改进。
eventually other inventors saw it and improved it.
在接下来的几百年里，人们为它添加了其他必要的元素，
Over the next couple hundred years, people added other essential elements to it,
包括浮阀，S型疏水阀，虹吸管，最终我们得到了-
including the float valve, and the S-trap, and siphon, and eventually we got-
&GT；&GT；扬声器2：鱼在哪里，
&gt;&gt; Speaker 2: Where are the fish,
不过，我想要鱼在我的马桶里？
though, I want fish in my toilet?
&gt；&gt；道格拉斯：你当然知道。
&gt;&gt; Douglas: Of course you do.
&gt；&gt；扬声器2：是的。
&gt;&gt; Speaker 2: Yeah.
&gt；&gt；Douglas：那么，他写了一本书，书名是《变形记》
&gt;&gt; Douglas: So, he wrote a book, and the title of the book was the Metamorphosis of
AJAX，他在1596年出版，他称之为AJAX。
Ajax, which he published in 1596, he called it The Ajax.
好，现在闪现一下，这是杰西·詹姆斯·加勒特。
Well, now flash forward a little bit, this is Jesse James Garrett.
他是旧金山的设计师和顾问。
He was a designer and consultant in San Francisco.
他在一个项目上
He was on a project where he was
咨询公司工程师，以及
consulting with the engineers of the company, and
他们告诉他，他们找到了这种为浏览器编写应用程序的方法。
they told him that they had found this way of writing applications for the browser.
即，不是每次用户单击时都进行页面替换，
That, instead of doing a page replacement each time the user clicks,
相反，他们将从浏览器向服务器发送一点点数据。
instead they will send a little bit of data from the browser to the server.
然后，服务器将发送回一个小响应，即浏览器中的JavaScript
The server will then send a small response back, JavaScript in the browser
然后将其显示在屏幕上，以便他们可以变得更好
will then display it on the screen so that they can get much better
使用这种技术的用户体验，并且它奏效了。
user experiences using this technique, and it worked.
他们遇到的问题是，他们无法说服自己的管理层
The problem they were having was, they couldn't convince their own management
这是一件可以接受的事情。
that this was an acceptable thing to do.
所以，他们问加勒特是否可以
So, they asked Garrett if he could
请向管理层解释这是个好主意。
please explain to management that this was a good idea.
所以，加勒特开始思考这个问题，
So, Garrett goes off and thinks about this problem,
并思考，我们如何呈现这个想法？
and thinks about, how do we present this idea?
他说，他在洗澡时想到了解决办法。
And, he says the solution came to him when he was in the shower.
我认为如果他在位的话，这会是一个更好的故事
I think it would have been a better story if he had been on the throne
做他的皇室生意，但他说他在洗澡
going about his royal business, but he says he was in the shower
当他想到他必须给它起个名字的时候。
when it occurred to him that he had to give it a name.
他给它起的名字是异步JavaScript和XML，或者
The name he gave it was Asynchronous JavaScript and XML, or
Ajax，2005年，他在他的公司网站上发布了一份关于这一点的备忘录
Ajax, and he published a memo about this on his company's website in 2005 and
几乎一夜之间就像病毒一样传播开来。
it went viral almost overnight.
每个人都在谈论Ajax和为Web编写Ajax应用程序，并且
Everybody was talking about Ajax and writing Ajax applications for the Web, and
它彻底改变了我们对浏览器和JavaScript的思考方式。
it completely transformed the way we think about browsers and JavaScript.
给出一些历史背景，网络来自文字处理，
Sort of give some historical context for this, the Web comes from word processing,
文字处理在历史上有两个非常不同的流派。
and word processing historically comes in two very distinct schools.
有一个二进制专有学校，从独立的设备开始，
There's the binary proprietary school, which started with standalone equipment,
然后共享逻辑，最后是个人计算机，这是
and then shared logic, and eventually personal computers, which was
在不同的时期被像IBM，Wang和今天的微软这样的公司所主导。
dominated at various times by companies like IBM, Wang, and today Microsoft.
然后是文本开放学校
Then, there is the textual open school
其中所有内容都始终以文本形式表示。
in which everything is represented as text all the time.
其中一个最早的例子是一个叫做“径流”的程序，这个程序是被开发出来的
One of the first examples of this is a program called Runoff that was developed
由麻省理工学院提供，而径流的目的是
by MIT, and Runoff was intended for
产生可以发送到各种打印机的文本。
producing text that could be sent to various printers.
所以，这里我们有一个径流文件的例子。
So, here we've got an example of a Runoff file.
如果一行以第一列中的句点开始，这意味着它是一个命令。
If a line starts with a period in column one, that means it's a command.
所以，在这种情况下，我们将跳过一行，然后我们将制表符四，我们将偏移四，
So, in this case, we'll skip one line, and then we'll tab four, we'll offset four,
依此类推，然后命令之间的文本将填充到页边距中。
and so on, and then the text between the commands will be filled into the margins.
现在这是一个非常流行的程序，它被从一个主机移植到另一个主机。
Now this was a very popular program, it was ported from one mainframe to another.
它到处移动，最终到达贝尔实验室，
It moved all over the place, eventually got to Bell Labs,
在那里它的名字被缩写为Roff，并且
where its name was shortened to ROFF, and
创建了它的其他版本，包括NROFF和Troff。
other versions of it were created, including NROFF and TROFF.
Troff是Unix社区排版的方式，
TROFF was the way the Unix community did typesetting,
做了很长一段时间的书。
made books for a long, long time.
与此同时，IBM公司有一位名叫查尔斯·戈德法布(Charles Goldfarb)的律师。
Meanwhile, there's an attorney at IBM named Charles Goldfarb.
他认为他可以做得更好，所以
He thinks he can do this stuff better, so
他开始了一个名为Generalized Markup Language的项目，这是一个
he begins a project called Generalized Markup Language, and this is an example of
一种通用的标记语言，在它的发展过程中是一种中点。
a Generalized Markup Language kind of midpoint through its evolution.
加价变得有点复杂了。
The markups got a little bit more complicated.
现在他在第一栏有一个冒号，然后是神秘的命令，
Now he's got a colon in column one, followed by cryptic command,
然后如果命令后面跟着一个点，
and then if the command is followed by a dot,
然后，他可以在线路的其余部分获得内容。
he can then have content on the remainder of the line.
所以，你开始混淆命令和内容，如果你
So, you're starting to mix up with the commands and the content, and if you're
熟悉HTML，您可能会奇怪地熟悉其中的一些命令，并且
familiar with HTML, some of these commands might be eerily familiar to you, and
这不是偶然的。
that's not accidental.
事实上，HTML来自于这一传统，除了EOL之外，
In fact, HTML comes out of this heritage, all of them except for EOL,
但你大概可以猜到那是什么意思。
but you can probably guess what that one means.
事实上，随着EML的发展，
In fact, as EML went through its evolution,
我们先是：E，然后是：，最后是&lt；&gt；，
we got :e, and then ::, and then finally &lt;&gt;,
你知道之后发生了什么。
and you know what happened after that.
所以，如果你曾经看过HTML实体，我们有一个与符号，
So, if you ever looked at HTML entities, we've got an ampersand,
密码和分号。
the cryptic code, and a semi-colon.
你在想，在什么奇怪的宇宙里
You're wondering, in what bizarre universe does it make sense to have a piece of
随机标点符号，然后是一个代码，以及另一个随机标点符号？
random punctuation, then a code, and another random piece of punctuation?
那是从哪里来的？
Where did that come from?
这就是它的来源，他用完了尖括号。
This is where it came from, he ran out of angle brackets.
没有其他办法让它看起来很好，所以
There was no other way to make it look nice, so
他选择了看起来很糟糕的东西，那么尖括号是从哪里来的呢？
he went with the awful looking thing, so where did the angle brackets come from?
尖括号的灵感来自Scribe。
The angle brackets were inspired by Scribe.
布莱恩·里德(Brian Reid)是卡内基梅隆大学(Carnegie Mellon)令人惊讶的聪明人，他制作了Scribe，
Brian Reid was an amazingly bright guy at Carnegie Mellon, who made Scribe,
他称之为文档编译器。
which he called a document compiler.
这是第一次有人把内容和
This is the first time someone got the separation between content and
格式正确。
formatting right.
抄写员是一件出色的作品，写字员可以把文件和
Scribe was a brilliant piece of work, Scribe could take documents and
把它们放到各种输出设备上，它就有了一个非常
put them to all sorts of output devices, and it had an extremely
很好的语言，有一个保留字符，那就是@符号。
nice language that there was one reserved character, which was the @ sign.
您可能会说@，然后是环境的名称，以及
You'd say @, then the name of an environment, and
然后你会有一些引用的东西，它们会受到那个环境的影响，而且
then you'd have some quoted stuff, which would be affected by that environment, and
他有六套引用字符。
he had six sets of quoting characters.
所以，你可以选择一个保证不会干扰
So, you could pick the one that's guaranteed not to interfere with
你放进去的内容，还有
the content that you're putting inside, and
你可以随心所欲地深嵌这些东西。
you could nest these things as deeply as you wanted.
而且，如果筑巢太深，他有特殊的开始和形式
And, if the nesting got too deep, he had special forms with begin and
结束了，所以他不关心意外匹配的东西。
end so that he didn't care about things accidentally matching.
所以，对于像章节和章节这样的长篇文章，
So, for long things like chapters and sections,
你可以这样把它们围起来，戈德法布看着这个
you could enclose them like that, and Goldfarb looked at this and
去了，尖括号，我不知道你会做尖括号，太棒了。
went, angle brackets, I didn't know you could do angle brackets, that's great.
所以，不幸的是，他从这里窃取了一些想法，
So, he stole some ideas from this, unfortunately,
他没有窃取足够的创意。
he didn't steal enough ideas.
所以，Scribe可以做的一件事就是参考书目。
So, one of the things that Scribe could do was bibliographies.
因为它是在大学里开发的，所以它必须能够处理学术问题
Since it was developed in a university, it has to be able to deal with academic
文件和诸如此类的东西，所以这里我们有一份技术报告和一本书的描述。
papers and such, so here we've got a description of a tech report and a book.
我相信这是文件格式第一次
I believe that this is the very first time that a document format was
被用作数据的表示，因为它看起来像JSON，对吗？
being used as a representation for data because it looks like JSON, right?
它是用逗号分隔的键值对，它看起来非常合理
It's key value pair separated by commas, and it's really reasonable looking and
甚至像细节这样的东西，就像这里一样等于1972。
even things like the details, like here equals 1972.
全年没有报价
There are no quotes around the year
因为在数字周围要求引号是很疯狂的，对吧？
because requiring quotes around numbers would be insane, right?
它真的很好，所以GML社区有了这个想法
It's just really good, so the GML community got the idea
从这个属性，但他们没有复制足够的好东西。
of attributes from this, but they didn't copy enough of the good stuff.
令人遗憾的是Tim Berners Lee没有对文本有更多的了解
It's a shame that Tim Berners Lee hadn't been more knowledgeable about text
处理系统，因为如果他把Web建立在Scribe的基础上
processing systems because, if he had based the Web on Scribe
而不是在SGML上，我们今天的生活会好得多，但他没有这样做。
instead of on SGML, our lives today would be so much better, but he didn't do that.
所以，我们可以看到径流激发了GML和Scribe，
So, we can see that Runoff inspires GML and Scribe,
Scribe帮助启发了SGML，但还不够，最终导致了HTML。
and Scribe helps inspire SGML, but not enough, and eventually that leads to HTML.